The things we make
الأشياء التي نصنعها
have one supreme quality --
لديها جودة عالية --
they live longer than us.
تعيش أطول منا.
We perish, they survive;
نهلك، فتبقى على قيد الحياة؛
we have one life, they have many lives,
لدينا حياة واحدة، لديها أرواح عديدة،
and in each life they can mean different things.
وفي كل حياة يمكنها أن تعني أشياء مختلفة.
Which means that, while we all have one biography,
ما يعني أنه، في حين نتوفر جميعنا على سيرة ذاتية واحدة،
they have many.
لديهم أكثر.
I want this morning to talk
أريد الحديث هذا الصباح
about the story, the biography -- or rather the biographies --
حول قصة، السيرة الذاتية -- أو بالأحرى السير الذاتية --
of one particular object,
لشيئ واحد على الخصوص،
one remarkable thing.
شيء رائع واحد.
It doesn't, I agree,
أوافقكم أنه لا
look very much.
يبدو شيء كثيرا.
It's about the size of a rugby ball.
إنه بقدر حجم كرة ركبي.
It's made of clay,
إنه مصنوع من الطين،
and it's been fashioned
وهو مطرز
into a cylinder shape,
على شكل أسطواني،
covered with close writing
مغطى بكتابات مغلقة
and then baked dry in the sun.
ومن ثم تم طبخها بالتجفيف في الشمس.
And as you can see,
وكما يمكنكم أن تروا،
it's been knocked about a bit,
قد تم ضربها بشكل طفيف،
which is not surprising
وهو أمر ليس مفاجئا
because it was made two and a half thousand years ago
لأنها كانت مصنوعة قبل ألفين وخمس مائة سنة
and was dug up
وتم إخراجها
in 1879.
سنة 1879.
But today,
لكن اليوم،
this thing is, I believe,
الأمر أنه، على ما أعتقد،
a major player
لاعب رئيسي
in the politics of the Middle East.
في سياسة الشرق الأوسط.
And it's an object
وهو موضوع
with fascinating stories
بقصص رائعة
and stories that are by no means over yet.
وقصص لم تنته بعد بأي حال من الأحوال.
The story begins
تبدأ القصة
in the Iran-Iraq war
في حرب العراق وإيران
and that series of events
وسلسلة الأحداث تلك
that culminated
والتي تكللت
in the invasion of Iraq
بغزو العراق
by foreign forces,
بالقوات الأجنبية،
the removal of a despotic ruler
إزالة حاكم مستبد
and instant regime change.
والتغيير الفوري لنظام الحكم.
And I want to begin
وأريد أن أبدأ
with one episode from that sequence of events
بحلقة واحدة من سلسلة الأحداث
that most of you would be very familiar with,
والتي قد يكون معظمكم مطلعا عليها،
Belshazzar's feast --
عيد بلشزار --
because we're talking about the Iran-Iraq war
لأننا نتحدث عن حرب العراق وإيران
of 539 BC.
لسنة 539 قبل الميلاد.
And the parallels
وأوجه الشبه
between the events
بين أحداث
of 539 BC and 2003 and in between
سنة 539 قبل الميلاد وسنة 2003 وما بينهما
are startling.
مذهلة.
What you're looking at is Rembrandt's painting,
ما تنظرون إليه هو لوحة رامبرانت،
now in the National Gallery in London,
في المعرض الوطني بلندن الآن،
illustrating the text from the prophet Daniel
موضحة النص من النبي دانيال
in the Hebrew scriptures.
في الكتب المقدسة العبرية.
And you all know roughly the story.
وكلكم يعرف القصة تقريبا.
Belshazzar, the son of Nebuchadnezzar,
بلشزار، ابن نبوخذ نصر،
Nebuchadnezzar who'd conquered Israel, sacked Jerusalem
نبوخذ نصر الذي غزا إسرائيل، عزل القدس
and captured the people
واعتقل الناس
and taken the Jews back to Babylon.
وأعاد اليهود إلى بابل.
Not only the Jews, he'd taken the temple vessels.
ليس فقط اليهود، قد أخذ كذلك أوعية المعبد.
He'd ransacked, desecrated the temple.
قام بنهب وتدنيس المعبد.
And the great gold vessels of the temple in Jerusalem
والأواني الذهبية العظيمة لمعبد القدس
had been taken to Babylon.
قد تم أخذها إلى بابل.
Belshazzar, his son,
ابنه بلشزار،
decides to have a feast.
قرر أن ينظم عيدا.
And in order to make it even more exciting,
ولجعله أكثر إثارة للاهتمام،
he added a bit of sacrilege to the rest of the fun,
أضاف شيء من تدنيس المقدسات إلى بقية المتعة،
and he brings out the temple vessels.
وهو يحضر أواني المعبد.
He's already at war with the Iranians,
هو بالفعل في حالة حرب مع الإيرانيين،
with the king of Persia.
مع ملك فارس.
And that night, Daniel tells us,
وفي تلك الليلة، أخبرنا دانييل،
at the height of the festivities
في ذروة الاحتفالات
a hand appeared and wrote on the wall,
ظهرت يد وكتبت على الحائط،
"You are weighed in the balance and found wanting,
"أنت توزن على الميزان وتوجد راغبا،
and your kingdom is handed over
ومملكتك سلمت
to the Medes and the Persians."
إلى الميديين والفرس."
And that very night
وفي تلك الليلة بالذات
Cyrus, king of the Persians, entered Babylon
كورش، ملك الفرس، دخل بابل
and the whole regime of Belshazzar fell.
فسقط نظام بلشزار بكامله.
It is, of course, a great moment
إنها وبالطبع لحظة عظيمة
in the history
في تاريخ
of the Jewish people.
اليهود.
It's a great story. It's story we all know.
إنها قصة عظيمة. إنها قصة نعرفها جميعا.
"The writing on the wall"
"الكتابة على الحائط"
is part of our everyday language.
هي جزء من لغتنا اليومية.
What happened next
ما حدث لاحقا
was remarkable,
كان رائعا،
and it's where our cylinder
وهنا حيث دخلت أسطوانتنا
enters the story.
إلى التاريخ.
Cyrus, king of the Persians,
كورش، ملك الفرس،
has entered Babylon without a fight --
دخل بابل بدون قتال --
the great empire of Babylon,
الإمبراطورية العظيمة لبابل،
which ran from central southern Iraq
والتي كانت تشمل من جنوب العراق
to the Mediterranean,
إلى البحر الأبيض المتوسط،
falls to Cyrus.
سقطت في يد كورش.
And Cyrus makes a declaration.
فأصدر كورش إعلانا.
And that is what this cylinder is,
وهذا ما هي هذه الأسطوانة عليه،
the declaration made by the ruler guided by God
الإعلان الذي أصدره الحاكم الموجه من الله
who had toppled the Iraqi despot
والذي كان قد أطاح بالطاغية العراقي
and was going to bring freedom to the people.
وكان على وشك تحقيق الحرية للشعب.
In ringing Babylonian --
بالرنين البابلي --
it was written in Babylonian --
كانت مكتوبة بالبابلية --
he says, "I am Cyrus, king of all the universe,
قد قال، "أنا كورش، ملك الكون،
the great king, the powerful king,
الملك العظيم، الملك القوي،
king of Babylon, king of the four quarters of the world."
ملك بابل، ملك الأرباع الأربعة من العالم."
They're not shy of hyperbole as you can see.
لا يخجلون من الغلو كما ترون.
This is probably
هذا على الأرجح
the first real press release
أول بيان صحفي حقيقي
by a victorious army
لجيش منتصر
that we've got.
لدينا.
And it's written, as we'll see in due course,
وهو مكتوب، كما سنرى في الوقت المناسب،
by very skilled P.R. consultants.
من طرف مستشاري علاقات عامة مهرة.
So the hyperbole is not actually surprising.
لذا فالغلو ليس في الواقع مفاجئا.
And what is the great king, the powerful king,
وما الذي سيقوم الملك العظيم والملك القوي
the king of the four quarters of the world going to do?
وملك البقاع الأربع للعالم به؟
He goes on to say that, having conquered Babylon,
يواصل ويقول أنه، وبغزو بابل،
he will at once let all the peoples
سيسمح لكل الناس دفعة واحدة
that the Babylonians -- Nebuchadnezzar and Belshazzar --
الذين قام البابليون -- نبوخذ نصر وبلشزار --
have captured and enslaved
باعتقالهم واستعبادهم
go free.
بتحريرهم.
He'll let them return to their countries.
سيسمح لهم بالعودة إلى دولهم.
And more important,
والأكثر أهمية،
he will let them all recover
أنه سيسمح لهم باستعادة
the gods, the statues,
الآلهة والتماثيل
the temple vessels
وأواني المعابد
that had been confiscated.
التي تم احتجازها.
All the peoples that the Babylonians had repressed and removed
كل الناس الذين قمعهم وأبعدهم البابليون
will go home,
سيذهبون إلى بيوتهم،
and they'll take with them their gods.
وسيأخذون معهم آلهتهم.
And they'll be able to restore their altars
وسيكونون قادرين على استعادة مذابحهم
and to worship their gods
وعبادة آلهتهم
in their own way, in their own place.
بطريقتهم الخاصة، في مكانهم الخاص.
This is the decree,
هذا هو المرسوم،
this object is the evidence
هذا الشيء هو الدليل
for the fact that the Jews,
على حقيقة أن اليهود،
after the exile in Babylon,
بعد النفي في بابل،
the years they'd spent sitting by the waters of Babylon,
السنوات التي قضوها جالسون قرب مياه بابل،
weeping when they remembered Jerusalem,
يبكون حين تذكروا القدس،
those Jews were allowed to go home.
أولئك اليهود سمح لهم بالعودة إلى بيوتهم.
They were allowed to return to Jerusalem
تم السماح لهم بالعودة إلى القدس
and to rebuild the temple.
وإعادة بناء المعبد.
It's a central document
إنها وثيقة مركزية
in Jewish history.
في تاريخ اليهود.
And the Book of Chronicles, the Book of Ezra in the Hebrew scriptures
وكتاب السجلات، كتاب عزرا في الكتاب المقدس العبري
reported in ringing terms.
ذكرت في مصطلحات رنانة.
This is the Jewish version
هذه هي النسخة اليهودية
of the same story.
لنفس القصة.
"Thus said Cyrus, king of Persia,
"ولذلك كما قال كورش، ملك فارس،
'All the kingdoms of the earth have the Lord God of heaven given thee,
'كل ممالك الأرض لها إله سماوي معطاة لهم،
and he has charged me
وقد كلفني
to build him a house in Jerusalem.
ببناء بيت له في القدس.
Who is there among you of his people?
والذي يوجد بينكم هناك من شعبه؟
The Lord God be with him,
الرب الإله سيكون معه،
and let him go up.'"
وسيرفعه."
"Go up" -- aaleh.
"ارتفع" -- آليه.
The central element, still,
لا يزال العنصر المركزي
of the notion of return,
لمفهوم العودة،
a central part
جزء مركزيا
of the life of Judaism.
في حياة اليهودي.
As you all know, that return from exile,
كما تعرفون جميعا، أن العودة من المنفى،
the second temple,
المعبد الثاني،
reshaped Judaism.
أعاد تشكيل اليهودية.
And that change,
وذلك التغيير،
that great historic moment,
تلك اللحظة التاريخية العظيمة،
was made possible by Cyrus, the king of Persia,
صارت ممكنة من طرف كورش ملك الفرس،
reported for us in Hebrew in scripture
تم تبليغها إلينا في الكتب المقدسة العبرية
and in Babylonian in clay.
بالبابلية في الطين.
Two great texts,
نصان عظيمان،
what about the politics?
ماذا عن السياسة؟
What was going on
ما الذي كان يحدث
was the fundamental shift in Middle Eastern history.
هو التحول الأساسي في تاريخ الشرق الأوسط.
The empire of Iran, the Medes and the Persians,
إمبراطورية إيران، الميديين والفرس،
united under Cyrus,
اتحدوا تحت إمرة كورش،
became the first great world empire.
أصبحوا أول إمبراطورية عالمية عظيمة.
Cyrus begins in the 530s BC.
بدأ كورش سنة 530 قبل الميلاد.
And by the time of his son Darius,
وبحلول فترة حكم ابنه داريوس،
the whole of the eastern Mediterranean
ساحل البحر الأبيض المتوسط الشرقي بكامله
is under Persian control.
يقع تحت سيطرة الفرس.
This empire is, in fact,
هذه الإمبراطورية هي، في الواقع،
the Middle East as we now know it,
الشرق الأوسط كما نعرفه،
and it's what shapes the Middle East as we now know it.
وهو ما شكل الشرق الأوسط كما نعرفه.
It was the largest empire the world had known until then.
كانت أكبر إمبراطورية قد عرفها العالم إلى حدود ذلك.
Much more important,
والأكثر أهمية،
it was the first
أنها كانت أول
multicultural, multifaith state
دولة متعددة الثقافات ومتعددة الديانات
on a huge scale.
على مقياس ضخم.
And it had to be run in a quite new way.
وتوجب أن تحكم بطريقة جديدة جدا.
It had to be run in different languages.
وجب أن تحكم بلغات مختلفة.
The fact that this decree is in Babylonian says one thing.
حقيقة أن هذا المرسوم كتب بالبابلية تقول أمرا واحدا.
And it had to recognize their different habits,
وقد توجب أن يتعرف على عاداتهم المختلفة،
different peoples, different religions, different faiths.
أشخاص مختلفون وديانات مختلفة وعقائد مختلفة.
All of those are respected by Cyrus.
كل تلك كان كورش يحترمها.
Cyrus sets up a model
قد وضع كورش نموذجا
of how you run
لكيف تحكم
a great multinational, multifaith, multicultural society.
مجتمعا عظيما متعدد الثقافات والديانات والجنسيات.
And the result of that
ونتيجة ذلك
was an empire that included the areas you see on the screen,
كان إمبراطورية شملت المناطق التي ترون على الشاشة،
and which survived for 200 years of stability
والتي عاشت 200 سنة من الاستقرار
until it was shattered by Alexander.
حتى تم تمزيقها من طرف الإسكندر.
It left a dream of the Middle East as a unit,
قد تركت حلم الشرق الأوسط كوحدة،
and a unit where people of different faiths
وحدة حيث يستطيع الناس من ديانات مختلفة
could live together.
العيش معا.
The Greek invasions ended that.
الغزو الإغريقي أنهى ذلك.
And of course, Alexander couldn't sustain a government
وبالطبع، لم يستطع الإسكندر أن يبقي على حكومة
and it fragmented.
وقد تجزأت.
But what Cyrus represented
لكن ما مثله سايروس
remained absolutely central.
قد بقي مركزيا تماما.
The Greek historian Xenophon
المؤرخ الإغريقي زينوفون
wrote his book "Cyropaedia"
ألف كتاب "سايروبايديا"
promoting Cyrus as the great ruler.
مروجا لكورش كحاكم عظيم.
And throughout European culture afterward,
وعلى امتداد الثقافة الأوروبية بعد ذلك،
Cyrus remained the model.
ظل كورش النموذج.
This is a 16th century image
هذه صورة القرن ال16
to show you how widespread
لإظهار مدى الانتشار الواسع
his veneration actually was.
الذي كان عليه تبجيله في الواقع.
And Xenophon's book on Cyrus
وكتاب زينوفون حول كورش
on how you ran a diverse society
حول كيف تحكم مجتمعا متنوعا
was one of the great textbooks
كان أحد أعظم الكتب الدراسية
that inspired the Founding Fathers
التي ألهمت الآباء المؤسسين
of the American Revolution.
للثورة الأمريكية.
Jefferson was a great admirer --
جيفرسون كان معجبا عظيما --
the ideals of Cyrus
المثل العليا لكورش
obviously speaking to those 18th century ideals
وبالحديث بوضوح إلى تلك المثل العليا للقرن ال18
of how you create religious tolerance
حول كيف تنشئ التسامح الديني
in a new state.
في دولة جديدة.
Meanwhile, back in Babylon,
في نفس الوقت، بالعودة إلى بابل،
things had not been going well.
لم تكن الأمور تجري على ما يرام.
After Alexander, the other empires,
بعد الإسكندر، الإمبراطوريات الأخرى،
Babylon declines, falls into ruins,
تراجعت بابل فوقعت في الأنقاض
and all the traces of the great Babylonian empire are lost --
وكل علامات الإمبراطورية البابلية العظيمة تلك قد فقدت --
until 1879
إلى حدود سنة 1879
when the cylinder is discovered
حين تم اكتشاف الأسطوانة
by a British Museum exhibition digging in Babylon.
من طرف معرض تحف بريطاني يحفر في بابل.
And it enters now another story.
وهي تدخل الآن قصة جديدة.
It enters that great debate
إنها تدخل جدالا عظيما
in the middle of the 19th century:
في منتصف القرن ال19:
Are the scriptures reliable? Can we trust them?
هل تلك النصوص موثوقة؟ هل يمكننا أن نثق بها؟
We only knew
قد عرفنا فقط
about the return of the Jews and the decree of Cyrus
بخصوص عودة اليهود ومرسوم كورش
from the Hebrew scriptures.
من الكتب المقدسة العبرية.
No other evidence.
لا دليل آخر.
Suddenly, this appeared.
فجأة ظهر هذا.
And great excitement
وحماس عظيم
to a world where those who believed in the scriptures
لعالم حيث أولئك الذين يؤمنون بالكتب المقدسة
had had their faith in creation shaken
قد تمت زعزعة إيمانهم بالنشوء
by evolution, by geology,
عن طريق التطور وعلم الأرض
here was evidence
كان دليلا هنا
that the scriptures were historically true.
على أن الكتب المقدسة كانت صحيحة تاريخيا.
It's a great 19th century moment.
إنها لحظة عظيمة في القرن 19.
But -- and this, of course, is where it becomes complicated --
لكن -- وهذا بالطبع هو حيث تصير معقدة --
the facts were true,
الحقائق كانت صحيحة،
hurrah for archeology,
مرحى لعلم الآثار،
but the interpretation was rather more complicated.
لكن التأويل كان أكثر تعقيدا بالأحرى.
Because the cylinder account and the Hebrew Bible account
لأن اعتبار الأسطوانة واعتبار الإنجيل العبري
differ in one key respect.
يختلفان في جانب رئيسي.
The Babylonian cylinder
الأسطوانة البابلية
is written by the priests
مكتوبة من طرف رجال دين
of the great god of Bablyon, Marduk.
الرب العظيم لبابل، ماردوك.
And, not surprisingly,
وبشكل غير مفاجئ،
they tell you that all this was done by Marduk.
يقولون أن كل هذا تم من طرف ماردوك.
"Marduk, we hold, called Cyrus by his name."
"ماردوك، قد نادى كورش باسمه."
Marduk takes Cyrus by the hand,
أخذ ماردوك بيد كورش،
calls him to shepherd his people
ودعاه لرعاية شعبه
and gives him the rule of Babylon.
وأعطاه حكم بابل.
Marduk tells Cyrus
ماردوك أخبر كورش
that he will do these great, generous things
أنه سيقوم بأشياء كريمة وعظيمة
of setting the people free.
بتحرير الشعب.
And this is why we should all be grateful to
ولهذا يجب أن نكون جميعا ممتنين
and worship Marduk.
ونعبد ماردوك.
The Hebrew writers
الكتاب العبريون
in the Old Testament,
في العهد القديم،
you will not be surprised to learn,
لن تتفاجؤوا بمعرفة،
take a rather different view of this.
أخذ وجهة نظر مختلفة بدلا من هذا.
For them, of course, it can't possibly by Marduk
بالنسبة لهم بالطبع ربما لن تكون بسبب ماردوك
that made all this happen.
الذي جعل كل هذا يحدث.
It can only be Jehovah.
يمكن فقط أن يكون يهوا.
And so in Isaiah,
نفس الشيء في أشعيا،
we have the wonderful texts
لدينا كل النصوص المذهلة
giving all the credit of this,
تعطي كل الفضل في هذا،
not to Marduk
لغير ماردوك
but to the Lord God of Israel --
لكن إلى الله رب إسرائيل --
the Lord God of Israel
إله إسرائيل
who also called Cyrus by name,
والذي دعى كورش كذلك باسمه،
also takes Cyrus by the hand
يأخذ كذلك بيد كورش
and talks of him shepherding his people.
ويتحدث عنه وعن رعايته لشعبه.
It's a remarkable example
إنه مثال ملحوظ
of two different priestly appropriations of the same event,
لاعتمادين كهنوتيين مختلفين لنفس الحدث،
two different religious takeovers
استحواذان دينيان مختلفان
of a political fact.
لحقيقة سياسية.
God, we know,
نعرف أن الله
is usually on the side of the big battalions.
هو عادة إلى جانب الكتائب الكبيرة.
The question is, which god was it?
السؤال هو، أي رب كان؟
And the debate unsettles
فزعزع الجدل
everybody in the 19th century
الجميع في القرن 19
to realize that the Hebrew scriptures
لإدراك أن الكتابات المقدسة العبرية
are part of a much wider world of religion.
هي جزء من عالم أوسع من الديانات.
And it's quite clear
ومن الواضح تماما
the cylinder is older than the text of Isaiah,
أن الأسطوانة أقدم من نص أشعيا،
and yet, Jehovah is speaking
وحتى الآن، يهوا يتحدث
in words very similar
بكلمات متشابهة جدا
to those used by Marduk.
لتلك المستخدمة من طرف ماردوك.
And there's a slight sense that Isaiah knows this,
وهناك قليل من المنطق أن أشعيا يعرف هذا،
because he says,
لأنه قال،
this is God speaking, of course,
هذا الرب يتحدث بالطبع،
"I have called thee by thy name
"لقد دعيتك باسمك
though thou hast not known me."
على الرغم من أنك لم تعرفني."
I think it's recognized
أظن أنه من المسلم
that Cyrus doesn't realize
أن كورش لا يدرك
that he's acting under orders from Jehovah.
أنه يتحرك بأمر من يهوا.
And equally, he'd have been surprised that he was acting under orders from Marduk.
وعلى قدم المساواة فقد تفاجأ لكونه يعمل تحت إمرة ماردوك.
Because interestingly, of course,
لأنه من المثير للاهتمام بالطبع
Cyrus is a good Iranian
كورش هو إيراني جيد
with a totally different set of gods
بطقم آلهة مختلف تماما
who are not mentioned in any of these texts.
والذين لم يذكروا في أي من النصوص.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's 1879.
تلك كانت سنة 1879.
40 years on
بعد 40 سنة
and we're in 1917,
ونحن في سنة 1917،
and the cylinder enters a different world.
والأسطوانة تدخل عالما مختلفا.
This time, the real politics
هذه المرة، السياسة الحقيقية
of the contemporary world --
للعالم المعاصر --
the year of the Balfour Declaration,
سنة إعلان وعد بلفور،
the year when the new imperial power in the Middle East, Britain,
السنة التي قررت فيها بريطانيا القوة الإمبريالية الجديدة في الشرق الأوسط
decides that it will declare
أن تعلن
a Jewish national home,
موطنا لليهود،
it will allow
سيسمح
the Jews to return.
لليهود بالعودة.
And the response to this
والرد على هذا
by the Jewish population in Eastern Europe is rhapsodic.
من طرف الساكنة اليهودية في أوروبا الشرقية كان عاطفيا.
And across Eastern Europe,
وعلى امتداد أوروبا الشرقية،
Jews display pictures of Cyrus
عرض اليهود صورة كورش
and of George V
وجورج الخامس
side by side --
جنبا إلى جنب --
the two great rulers
الحاكمان العظيمان
who have allowed the return to Jerusalem.
الذين سمحا بالعودة إلى القدس.
And the Cyrus cylinder comes back into public view
وقد عادت أسطوانة كورش للعرض العلني
and the text of this
ونصوص هذا
as a demonstration of why what is going to happen
كعرض لكيف و لماذا و ما الذي حدث
after the war is over in 1918
بعد نهاية الحرب سنة 1918
is part of a divine plan.
هو جزء من خطة إلهية.
You all know what happened.
تعرفون جميعا ما الذي حصل.
The state of Israel is setup,
تم الإعداد لدولة إسرائيل،
and 50 years later, in the late 60s,
وبعد 50 سنة، في نهاية الستينات،
it's clear that Britain's role as the imperial power is over.
كان من الواضح أن دور البريطانيين كإمبريالية قد انتهى.
And another story of the cylinder begins.
وقصة أخرى للأسطوانة قد بدأت.
The region, the U.K. and the U.S. decide,
المنطقة والمملكة المتحدة والولايات المتحدة قررت،
has to be kept safe from communism,
أنه يجب أن تبقى آمنة من الإشتراكية،
and the superpower that will be created to do this
والقوة العظمى التي سيتم إنشاؤها للقيام بذلك
would be Iran, the Shah.
ستكون الشاه في إيران.
And so the Shah invents an Iranian history,
وبالتالي ابتكر الشاه تاريخا إيرانيا،
or a return to Iranian history,
للعودة إلى التاريخ الإيراني،
that puts him in the center of a great tradition
والتي تجعله في مركز التقليد العظيم
and produces coins
وتنتج قطعا نقدية
showing himself
مظهرا نفسه
with the Cyrus cylinder.
مع أسطوانة كورش.
When he has his great celebrations in Persepolis,
حين أقام احتفاله العظيم في برسبوليس،
he summons the cylinder
أمر باستدعاء الأسطوانة
and the cylinder is lent by the British Museum, goes to Tehran,
فتمت إعارة الأسطوانة من طرف المتحف البريطاني لتذهب إلى طهران
and is part of those great celebrations
وتكون جزء من تلك الاحتفالات العظيمة
of the Pahlavi dynasty.
للدولة البهلوية.
Cyrus cylinder: guarantor of the Shah.
أسطوانة كورش: الضامن للشاه.
10 years later, another story:
بعد 10 سنوات، قصة أخرى:
Iranian Revolution, 1979.
الثورة الإيرانية سنة 1979.
Islamic revolution, no more Cyrus;
الثورة الإسلامية، لا مزيد من كورش؛
we're not interested in that history,
لسنا مهتمين بذلك التاريخ،
we're interested in Islamic Iran --
نحن مهتمون بإيران الإسلامية --
until Iraq,
إلى غاية العراق،
the new superpower that we've all decided should be in the region,
القوة العظمى الجديدة التي قررنا جميعا أنها يجب أن تكون في المنطقة،
attacks.
تهاجم.
Then another Iran-Iraq war.
ثم حرب إيرانية-عراقية.
And it becomes critical for the Iranians
وقد أصبحت حاسمة للإيرانية
to remember their great past,
لتذكر ماضيهم العظيم،
their great past
ماضيهم العظيم
when they fought Iraq and won.
حين حاربوا العراق وانتصروا.
It becomes critical to find a symbol
يصبح حاسما إيجاد رمز
that will pull together all Iranians --
سيوحد جميع الإيرانيين مع بعضهم --
Muslims and non-Muslims,
المسلمين وغير المسلمين،
Christians, Zoroastrians, Jews living in Iran,
المسيحيين والزرادشتيين واليهود الذين يعيشون في إيران،
people who are devout, not devout.
الأشخاص المتدينون وغير المتدينون.
And the obvious emblem is Cyrus.
والرمز البديهي هو كورش.
So when the British Museum and Tehran National Musuem
وبالتالي حين قام المتحف البريطاني ومتحف طهران الوطني
cooperate and work together, as we've been doing,
بالتعاون والعمل معا، كما كنا نفعل،
the Iranians ask for one thing only
طلب الإيرانيون أمرا واحدا فقط
as a loan.
كقرض.
It's the only object they want.
إنه الأمر الوحيد الذي يريدونه.
They want to borrow the Cyrus cylinder.
يريديون إستعارة أسطوانة كورش.
And last year,
وفي السنة الماضية،
the Cyrus cylinder went to Tehran
توجهت الأسطوانة إلى طهران
for the second time.
للمرة الثانية.
It's shown being presented here, put into its case
هنا تظهر معروضة، موضوعة في صندوقها
by the director of the National Museum of Tehran,
من طرف مدير متحف طهران الوطني،
one of the many women in Iran in very senior positions,
واحدة من العديد من النساء في إيران في منصب كبير جدا،
Mrs. Ardakani.
السيدة أرداكاني.
It was a huge event.
كان حدثا ضخما.
This is the other side of that same picture.
هذا هو الجزء الآخر من نفس الصورة.
It's seen in Tehran
تمت رؤيتها في طهران
by between one and two million people
من طرف ما بين واحد إلى مليوني شخص
in the space of a few months.
في فضاء بضعة أشهر.
This is beyond any blockbuster exhibition
هذا أضخم من أي إقبال على معرض
in the West.
في الغرب.
And it's the subject of a huge debate
وهو موضوع مناظرة كبيرة
about what this cylinder means, what Cyrus means,
حول ما تعنيه هذه الأسطوانة، ما يعنيه كورش،
but above all, Cyrus as articulated through this cylinder --
لكن فوق كل شيء، كورش كما هو موضح في هذه الأسطوانة --
Cyrus as the defender of the homeland,
كورش كحامي الوطن الأم،
the champion, of course, of Iranian identity
البطل وبالطبع الهوية الإيرانية
and of the Iranian peoples,
ومن أجل الشعب الإيراني،
tolerant of all faiths.
متسامحا مع كل الأديان.
And in the current Iran,
وفي إيران الحالية،
Zoroastrians and Christians have guaranteed places
الزرادشتيين والمسيحيون لديهم أماكن مضمونة
in the Iranian parliament, something to be very, very proud of.
في البرلمان الإيراني، أمر سيكونون جد فخورين به.
To see this object in Tehran,
لرؤية هذا الشيء في طهران،
thousands of Jews living in Iran
آلاف من اليهود الذي يعيشون في إيران
came to Tehran to see it.
جاؤوا إلى طهران لرؤيته.
It became a great emblem,
أصبح رمزا عظيما،
a great subject of debate
موضوعا عظيما للمناظرة
about what Iran is at home and abroad.
حول ما هي عليه إيران داخليا وخارجيا.
Is Iran still to be the defender of the oppressed?
هل لا تزال إيران المدافع عن المضطهدين؟
Will Iran set free the people
هل ستحرر إيران الناس
that the tyrants have enslaved and expropriated?
الذين صادرهم واستعبدهم الطغاة؟
This is heady national rhetoric,
هذا هو الخطاب الوطني المثير،
and it was all put together
وقد تم وضعها كلها مجتمعة
in a great pageant
في موكب عظيم
launching the return.
مطلقين العودة.
Here you see this out-sized Cyrus cylinder on the stage
هنا ترون أسطوانة كورش الضخمة هذه على الخشبة
with great figures from Iranian history
مع شخصيات عظيمة من التاريخ الإيراني
gathering to take their place
مجتمعين لأخذ مكانهم
in the heritage of Iran.
في تراث إيران.
It was a narrative presented
لقد كان سردا مقدما
by the president himself.
من طرف الرئيس نفسه.
And for me,
وبالنسبة لي،
to take this object to Iran,
أن آخذ هذا الشيء إلى إيران،
to be allowed to take this object to Iran
أن يسمح لي بأخذ هذا الشيء إلى إيران
was to be allowed to be part
كان ليسمح به ليكون جزء
of an extraordinary debate
من مناظرة رائعة
led at the highest levels
تقام على أعلى مستويات
about what Iran is,
حول ماهية إيران،
what different Irans there are
ما هي الإيرانات المختلفة الموجودة
and how the different histories of Iran
وكيف قد تشكل التواريخ المختلفة لإيران
might shape the world today.
العالم اليوم.
It's a debate that's still continuing,
إنها مناظرة لا تزال مستمرة،
and it will continue to rumble,
وستستمر في القعقعة،
because this object
لأن الموضوع
is one of the great declarations
هو أحد أعظم الإعلانات
of a human aspiration.
للطموح البشري.
It stands with the American constitution.
يقف مع الدستور الأمريكي.
It certainly says far more about real freedoms
هي بالتأكيد تقول أكثر بكثير حول الحريات الحقيقية
than Magna Carta.
من ماغنا كارتا.
It is a document that can mean so many things,
إنها وثيقة يمكنها أن تعني الكثير من الأشياء،
for Iran and for the region.
لإيران والمنطقة.
A replica of this
نسخة من هذا
is at the United Nations.
هي في الأمم المتحدة.
In New York this autumn, it will be present
في نيويورك هذا الخريف، سيتم عرضها
when the great debates
حين تنعقد المناظرة العظيمة
about the future of the Middle East take place.
حول مستقبل الشرق الأوسط.
And I want to finish by asking you
وأريد أن أختم بسؤالكم
what the next story will be
عما ستكون عليه القصة الموالية
in which this object figures.
حيث يعتبر هذا الشيء.
It will appear, certainly,
سيظهر بالتأكيد
in many more Middle Eastern stories.
في العديد من قصص الشرق الأوسط الأخرى.
And what story of the Middle East,
وأي قصة للشرق الأوسط،
what story of the world,
أي قصة للعالم،
do you want to see
تريدون رؤيتها
reflecting what is said,
تعكس ما أقوله،
what is expressed in this cylinder?
ما هو معبر عنه في هاته الأسطوانة؟
The right of peoples
حق الناس
to live together in the same state,
في العيش معا في نفس الدولة،
worshiping differently, freely --
يعبدون باختلاف، بحرية --
a Middle East, a world,
شرق أوسط وعالم
in which religion is not the subject of division
حيث لا يكون الدين موضوع اختلاف
or of debate.
أو مناظرة.
In the world of the Middle East at the moment,
في عالم الشرق الأوسط حاليا،
the debates are, as you know, shrill.
المناظرة هي كما تعرفون شديدة.
But I think it's possible
لكن أظنه من الممكن
that the most powerful and the wisest voice of all of them
أن أكثر الأصوات قوة وحكمة منهم
may well be the voice
قد يكون صوت
of this mute thing,
هذا الشيء الأخرس،
the Cyrus cylinder.
إسطوانة كورش.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)